<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Letters from Shiraz ✍</title>
    <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Letters from Shiraz ✍</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Descartes</title>
      <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/descartes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/descartes/</guid>
      <description>Descartes differs from [[Francis Bacon]] in that he has a unique notion of man&amp;rsquo;s position with respect to both God and nature. In his early thought, he believed that he could construct a fundamental science on the basis of mathematics. This was to allow for a mathematical representation of all motion so man could truly master nature, an objective that Bacon first laid out. Descartes&#39; project was called into question by the omnipotent God of [[nominalism]], which undermined the certainty of mathematics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Francis Bacon</title>
      <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/francis-bacon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/francis-bacon/</guid>
      <description>Francis Bacon is often characterized as the father of modern science. He was a nominalist that rejected the existence of anything other than individual bodies in nature, which perform individual acts.
Bacon was not concerned with what nature is, but rather how nature works. His goal was not theory or speculation but the practical betterment of the human condition. When we understand the properties of particulars, we will be able to bring them together in ways that produce the effects that are desired.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ibn Taymiyya</title>
      <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/ibn-taymiyya/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/ibn-taymiyya/</guid>
      <description>Ibn Taymiyya was a sigificant Hanbali jurist-theologian. Known for his polemical stances, his thought must nonetheless be understood with reference to a broader method andtheological vision. He builds off, albeit in a critical, the thought of [[Ibn Sina]], [[Abu Hamid al-Ghazali]], and [[Fakhr al-Din al-Razi]].
Theology In part, Ibn Taymiyya&amp;rsquo;s purpose in delving into theology is to motivate worship and obedience to God. Ibn Taymiyya portrays God as perpetually active, personal, and intimately involved in human affairs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martin Luther</title>
      <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/martin-luther/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/martin-luther/</guid>
      <description>As a young man, Luther became a follower of [[William of Ockham]], but was troubled by the impenetrability and arbitrary of the God described in [[nominalism]]. His quest for certainty was tied with struggle against corruption in the church. Luther rejected the redemptive power of works on nominalistic grounds. Since whatever man wills, God also wills, sin could only be remitted through right willing. His answer to indulgences was an answer to the problem of the nominalist God: &amp;ldquo;faith alone saves&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petrarch</title>
      <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/petrarch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/petrarch/</guid>
      <description>Portrait of Petrarch, French School
Petrarch remarks that there was nothing more deeply imprinted in his mind than Heraclitus&#39; saying that &amp;ldquo;everything exists by strife&amp;rdquo;. He saw continual change everywhere, starting with inanimate things and extending to the spiritual realm. Human life is especially beset by strife, especially the greater war that takes place within the soul. Even in times of peace, we are still attacked by our own passions, and to maintain his freedom, man must forever battle temptation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ethical Dilemma</title>
      <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/the-ethical-dilemma/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/the-ethical-dilemma/</guid>
      <description>Ibn Taymiyya places emphasis on wasat (moderation), as the most sound position is often the one which “unites the elements of truth that different views contain and steers clear from the error they contain”. This justifies his engagement and limited openness with heterodox ideologies, such as that of the Mu’tazilites. The Mu&amp;rsquo;tazilites argued that actions are inherently good or bad because they are known by reason to be so. According to them, the divine law only confirms and particularizes this knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thomas Hobbes</title>
      <link>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/thomas-hobbes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 03:32:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lettersfromshiraz.com/posts/thomas-hobbes/</guid>
      <description>Hobbes claims that motion is teleologically determined and, unlike nominalists, mechanical as well. Man is moved not by his natural impulses, divine inspiration, or free will, but by a sucession of causal motions. Humans are no different than nature, and human objects will remain in its given motion unless it is contravened by collision with another body. This collision is conflict because it limits motion, and it intantiates as war between men.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
